Guide to the John Rodman Paul Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1925?-1971, undated; Series III
  - "Final Report on Consultations on Poliomyelitis Carried Out in Israel, 27 June-6 July 1950, in Relation to Their Current (1950) Epidemic" (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - "Memorial to Dr. William T. Salter", 1952 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - "Report on Epidemiological Observations on The Hemorrhagic Fever in May-June, 1953 " [with William H. McClure] (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - James Stevens Simmons obituary, [1954] (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - "Report of the Medical Mission to the U.S.S.R.", 1956 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - "Poliomyelitis: Historical Aspects of the Development of Research Investigations" [lecture], 1957 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - "Haven Emerson, October 19, 1874- May 21,1957", 1957-1958 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - "Poliomyelitis" in Textbook of Medicine, 1957-1960 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - "Triennial Report [1955-57 incl.] of the Regional Laboratory of the Americas", 1958 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - "Three Wars, Three Plagues"
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Drafts, 1958-1963 (Box 18, Folder 20-21)
  - "Casual reports by J. R. Paul from several European countries where there has been a brief opportunity to learn of poliomyelitis work", 1959 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - "Epidemiology of poliomyelitis and its natural spread" [Copenhagen], 1960 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - "Joseph Edwin Smadel"
    - Clinical Epidemiology, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Reviews, 1965-1967 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Autobiographical sketch for McGraw-Hill Modern Men of Science, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - "Dick Shope" for Century Association, [1966] (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - "Dean Winternitz and the Rebirth of the Yale Medical School", 1969 (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - "History of the Neurotropic Virus Disease Commission", 1970 (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - "Thomas J. Francis, Jr., M.D., 1900-1969", [1970] (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - "Stanhope Bayne-Jones, M.D., 1888-1970", 1971 (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - History of Poliomyelitis, [1971]
    - Armstrong, Charles, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 33)
    - Funding, 1965-1970 (Box 19, Folder 34-35)
    - Notes, 1966-1970, undated (Box 19, Folder 36)
    - Permissions letters, 1967-1970 (Box 19, Folder 37)
    - Publisher search, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 38)
    - Yale University Press, 1965-1971, undated (Box 19, Folder 39)
  - An Account of the American Epidemiological Society, [1973]
    - Background material, 1927-1970, undated (Box 19, Folder 40-41)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1971, undated (Box 19, Folder 42-45)
    - Histories, 1927-1952 (Box 20, Folder 46)
    - Planning and funding, 1969-1971, undated (Box 20, Folder 47)
  - "Two Early North American Archeologists of the Southwest" [with Leita H. Paul], 1971 (Box 20, Folder 48)
  - "Birds Outside a Hospital Window", Undated (Box 20, Folder 49)
  - "Preventive Medicine Experiences from the Clinical Approach; The Present System at the Yale School of Medicine" [lecture], Undated (Box 20, Folder 50)
  - "Swedish Holiday", Undated (Box 20, Folder 51)
  - Book reviews, [1943?], 1967, undated (Box 20, Folder 52)
- Personal Papers and Photographs, 1920-1992, undated; Series IV
  The series includes personal and biographical materials and photographs. It is highlighted by the detailed handwritten journals Paul kept on his travels abroad during and after World War II. Of special interest is the journal labeled "War Diary," which covers Paul's assignment as director of the Neurotropic Virus Disease Commission of the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board (AFEB). Entries in the diary chronicle his work on viruses in North Africa and and the Middle East. At the end of his life, Paul had a typescript transcription made for his Japan diary, thinking that this might be published. Dorothy Horstmann may have been following his idea for the 1992 typescript of the War Diary was found in Horstmann's papers and reflects her editorial hand. It should be noted that the series includes only this transcript of the "War Diary" and not the original volume.
  The journals are augmented by photographs taken during Paul's travels, which are listed at the end of the series. The series also contains portraits of Paul and photographs of professional colleagues and groups. There are also records relating to several tributes to Paul in the series.
  - General, 1920-1961 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1943-1971, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Curricula vitae and bibliographies, 1932-1970 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Interview by George Rosen, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Journals
    - War Diary, 1943 [Volume I printout from floppy disk, Volume II typescript], 1992 (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    - Japan, 1946, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - London, Copenhagen, Stockholm, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Alaska, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Korea, 1953 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Soviet Union, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Memorabilia, 1940, 1955, undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Obituaries, 1971-1972 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Tributes
    - General, 1961-1975, undated (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - University of Chicago honorary degree, [1956] (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Festschrift, portrait, dinner, 1961-1962, undated (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Virology and Epidemiology Contributions in honor of John Rodman Paul, 1961 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Nomination for the Bronfman Prize for Public Health Achievement, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits, [1949?]-1974, undated (Box 22, Folder 20)
    - Alaska, [1950?] (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Cairo, Egypt, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - Paul, John Rodman with colleagues, [193-]-1960, undated (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Professional [historical and contemporary portraits], 1931-1954, undated (Box 22, Folder 24)
    - Projects, 1936-1956, undated (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Yale School of Medicine, 1945-1961 (Box 23, Folder 26-27)
    - Unidentified, Undated (Box 23, Folder 28)